Okay today's דף Daf we are ahead yet again and I know
we'll have to figure out how to deal with being so far
ahead, should be our biggest problem. Anyway we pick up on
מ"ט עמוד ב' Mem-Tet Amud Bet 49b where it looks like we
will God willing go through דף נ' Daf Nun today. So we
start with the משנה. Mishnah. We've been now this פרק Perek has
been focused on the prohibition of the נזיר Nazir not becoming טמא
Tamei but it starts of course with the idea that a נזיר
Nazir can become טמא Tamei for מת מצוה Meit Mitzvah and we
spent a lot of yesterday and the day before understanding how we
learn that out from the verse that מת מצוה Meit Mitzvah overrides
the restrictions of a נזיר Nazir and a כהן גדול Kohen Gadol
and even when those are piled on one another going to do
a ברית מילה Brit Milah קרבן פסח Korban Pesach anyway the overriding
nature of מת מצוה Meit Mitzvah and then the only interesting question
became the question about priorities about whose קדושה Kedusha do you preserve
protect first if there's some choice to be made. Our משנה Mishnah
turns to the actual nature of the parameters of the restrictions of
a נזיר Nazir being טמא Tamei and in some way we dealt
with all the restrictions in an earlier פרק Perek שלשה מינים Shlosha
Minim but here we are dealing with more the specific parameters of
טומאה. Tumah. To some degree it's a question about what types of
things cause טומאה. Tumah. If that were true we could go ahead
and learn major sections of מסכת טהרות Masseches Taharos so we will
not be overly focusing on that but it will be giving us
some of the basic parameters of the amounts of a dead body
and the parts of a dead body and the minimum sizes that
cause טומאה Tumah but an interesting הלכה Halacha that we will see
is that there are a few cases of something that cause טומאת
מת Tumat Meis but nevertheless the נזיר Nazir does not shave his
head as a result of is not prohibited against and so there
are some like arbitrary things which we learn from tradition הלכה למשה
מסיני Halacha L'Moshe MiSinai that even though they cause טומאת מת Tumat
Meis are somehow excluded from this prohibition. And that is very relevant
because we learn the parameters of טומאת כהנים Tumat Kohanim and the
restrictions of טומאת כהנים Tumat Kohanim from the restrictions of the נזיר.
Nazir. So those exceptions although initially some of those exceptions will seem
obscure and irrelevant there are some that will be relevant so keep
your eye open for that. Already a question? Yes.
Just trying to bring it to the level of practicality. So I
understand that טומאה Tumah for a כהן Kohen is relevant today. Right.
Are any of these other טומאות Tumos relevant at all in any
fact?
No unless somebody decides to be a נזיר. Nazir. No. Okay so
now we take a look at the משנה. Mishnah. The answer is
no. על אלו טומאות הנזיר מגלח. Al Elu Tumos HaNazir Megaleiach. So
the משנה Mishnah on מ"ט עמוד ב' Mem-Tet Amud Bet 49b על
אלו טומאות הנזיר מגלח Al Elu Tumos HaNazir Megaleiach on the following
טומאות Tumos are the ones that a נזיר Nazir will shave his
head for that destroy the current count of the נזירות Nezirut you
have to bring a קרבן Korban you have to start again and
so on. על המת ועל כזית מן המת Al HaMeis V'Al Kezayis
Min HaMeis on an entire corpse not even an entire corpse even
just a כזית Kezayis size of the flesh of the corpse okay
so the amount of כזית Kezayis is when you think about it
a little ironic because normally we use כזית Kezayis for an amount
for foods and here but it also becomes sort of like a
default size like some very often there's a whole different ranges of
minimum sizes but כזית Kezayis often is assumed to be like a
default even not in the context of food. Anyway for whatever reason
the tradition here is that even an olive size of the flesh
of a corpse causes טומאת מת Tumat Meis and טומאת מת באהל
Tumat Meis Ba'Ohel I should say the first things on this list
until we get to the very end there will be a small
second list are things that cause טומאת מת Tumat Meis even if
you're under the same roof. Okay come back to a bigger קל
וחומר Kal V'Chomer if there are three ways of conducting
טומאה Tumah for a מת Meis מגע Magah היסט Heseit and or
being נושא Nosei carrying but it's a form of like moving or
whatever don't worry about some of the differences and being in the
אהל. Ohel. אהל Ohel could be under the same roof it could
mean you're on top of the מת Meis or the מת Meis
is on top of you those are three forms of אהל. Ohel.
By אהל Ohel the תורה Torah more emphasizes the entire dead body
אדם כי ימות באהל Adam Ki Yamut Ba'Ohel right if an אדם
Adam is made באהל Ba'Ohel I mean it also talks about לכל
נפש אדם L'Chol Nefesh Adam you know other types of טומאה Tumah
as well but anyway to some degree you can conceptually see that
what we're trying to do by טומאת אהל Tumat Ohel is define
really something that's to some degree a part that's representative of the
whole like and that's why there's slightly different שיעורים Shiurim there are
a few small things that the size is so small and because
of the object we're dealing with that cause טומאה Tumah by מגע
Magah but not in the אהל. Ohel. But the first list are
things that cause טומאה Tumah in the אהל. Ohel. Okay. Yes.
Just so I have a visual image if I'm in the basement
and the מת Meis is in the attic and the floor's in
between?
Okay so that's a good question. There are that's what all מסכת
אהלות Masseches Oholos is about. There are ways in which if basically
there's a roof on top of the מת Meis and there's a
טפח Tefach there that the roof is sort of אהל Ohel over
a טפח Tefach of air space right of a
not of a vacuum what's the word I'm looking for of a
cavity or something anyway then it stops the טומאה Tumah from going
through.
Okay however. The problem about flying over a cemetery is because there
is not a טפח tefach because it's all just the dirt. Now
you might say one minute, the coffin has a טפח, tefach, but
the coffin is a separate הלכה, halacha, it becomes seen as an
extension of the מת, meit, so it doesn't stop the טומאה. tumah.
Okay, but yes, if there is a roof between and there's a
טפח tefach between the roof, under most circumstances that will stop the
טומאה tumah from going through.
What about looking at the down also stairs when you go there
and
yeah, but if you're also below it and yeah, I mean there's
ways in which it stops, you know, those are in the entire
מסכת. masechet. Okay. אלו למטמא טומאת הנזיר ומגלח aleu l'metamei tumat hanazir
umegaleach על המת al hameit an entire corpse ועל כזית מן המת
v'alkezayit min hameit on just a כזית kezayit ועל כזית נצל, v'alkezayit
netzel, now a כזית kezayit of נצל netzel we are going to
see what this means in the גמרא, gemara, but it basically is
a type of the flesh that has sort of dissolved, decomposed, liquefied,
and then it's recongealed, okay, so basically it has a similar status
as the flesh itself ועל מלא תרווד רקב v'al melo tarvad rekav
and on a ladle-sized
spoonful, how much, what type of ladle are we talking about, whatever,
we'll see in the גמרא, gemara, but on a certain quantity of
filled with the decomposed matter of the body, so it's not the,
it's not flesh that liquefied and solidified, it's more like dust, the,
you know, ashes to ashes, dust to dust, when it has become
dust, okay. Yep, we will see, some of these are like total
הלכה למשה מסיני.
halacha l'moshe misinai.
No, that would be ashes, that would be אפר, efer, this is
a natural decomposition. Okay.
על שדרה ועל גולגולת al shidra v'al gulgollet on the spinal cord
and the skull, whether that means the combination or either, we'll see,
ועל אבר מן המת v'al eiver min hameit on a full limb
of the dead body, and not only that, ועל אבר מן החי,
v'al eiver min hachai, now this is something you might not have
expected, but if a limb falls off of a person who is
alive, that also causes טומאת מת, tumat meit,
so the limb is actually interesting because, you know, until now I
was saying that these things sort of are representative of the whole,
there's actually a word for that, for an English term, that where
a part represents the whole, synecdoche, synecdoche, I always get it mixed
up with Schenectady, New
York, synecdoche, okay, so anyway
here
it's interesting because here the person isn't dead, right, now we start,
now start channeling Monty Python, I'm not dead, anyway, the person isn't
dead, but you have a limb, an entire limb is seen as,
so it's not representing the whole corpse, but in itself is somehow
seen as itself a type of a מת, meit, so that's particularly
interesting.
Even if your own? Yeah, so I mean your own, let's
say you had god forbid
had to have an amputation, you'd have to bury it, right?
Well, I mean,
I
mean, for, I mean,
whatever, yeah, there'll be implications, right. Okay, so anyway, so on a
limb that fell off from life שיש עליו בשר כראוי, sheyesh alav
basar karauy, now these, these ideas of אבר eiver means it can't
just be the bones, there has to be enough flesh. How much
is enough? So the basic amount of enough is that if this
bone were, if this limb were attached to the body, there would
be enough flesh so that the limb could heal, so that it
could like, you know, it could develop a scar and heal and
whatever, and so that's considered, so when we're thinking about it as
a limb, it's not only bone but also a certain amount of
the actual flesh, ועל חצי קב עצמות v'al chatzi kav atzamot on
a half of a קב, kav, I don't, did not look up
how much this is, anyway, but a few ounces, I guess, ounce
is actually what is, ounce is a volume measurement, weight, weight, weight,
whatever it is, all these are volume measurements. Anyway, on a half
of a קב kav of bones. Now here I want to stop
for a moment because if you look at תוספות tosafot על חצי
קב עצמות, al chatzi kav atzamot, this is the first of the
exceptions that I had mentioned, תוספות tosafot says, first of all, well,
first
תוספות tosafot says ומיירי שבאו מרוב מניינו או מרוב בניינו, umairi shebau
merov minyano o merov binyano, so basically it's not just random bones,
it has to be that you had because a certain quantity of
bones that either was a majority of the number of bones in
the body or that they was a majority of the structure of
the body. Now that in itself causes טומאה, tumah, רוב מנין ורוב
בניין, rov minyan v'rov binyan, טומאה באוהל, tumah b'ohel, but let's say
then those bones were crushed, okay, and then you scooped out from
that pile of crushed bones and the original pile was רוב מנין
ורוב בניין rov minyan v'rov binyan a חצי קב, chatzi kav, that
would be the case of חצי קב, chatzi kav, so we're not
just talking about random bones, it has to be drawn from, again,
I don't know exactly does it mean you need a little bit
of each of those bones, okay, but it has to be coming
from a type of a bone structure, a number of bones, a
quantity of bones that would itself cause טומאת מת באוהל, tumat meit
b'ohel, רוב מנין ורוב בניין, rov minyan v'rov binyan, but then תוספות
tosafot says the next line which is important.
Half a quart is pretty big then.
I mean, somebody, if Tzvi were here, he'd be looking it up.
One and a half to two and a half quarts.
One and a half to two and a half quarts. Okay, I
mean, that's not so big, like, what's one of those thin bottles
of milk, that's like what, that's a half a quart?
Sure, cup's like a.
What?
Two liters?
Those thin things, it's a quart.
Okay, and what did you say? One and a half to 2.65.
Okay, like a bottle of those big bottles of Coke.
Okay, okay. So, it's not such a trivial amount. Now, relevant to
that, תוספות Tosafot *Tosafot* says like this, the other point is, let
me get to the other point.
Maybe like a lot of little bones from different people.
What? No, well, we're going to get to that about different people.
No, but the basic answer is no. Now תוספות Tosafos *Tosafot* says
here,
now if you take a look go down in that תוספות Tosafos
*Tosafot*, the line starts with the word רוב בנינו *Rov Binyano*, okay?
You see the line רוב בנינו *Rov Binyano*, like the third line.
רוב בנינו *Rov Binyano* מפרש לקמן *mefarish lekaman* שני שוקים *shne shokim*,
either the two hips or וירך אחד *veyarech echad*, and one thigh,
או איפכא *o ipecha*, or the opposite. Okay? Now thigh bones are
very big, anyway, or hip bones are big. Anyway, ואף על פי
*ve'af al pi* here's the point I wanted to look at. So
that's the, that's considered the most of the structure. Now, ואף על
פי שמיטמא באהל ברוב הקב *ve'af al pi shemitamei b'ohel b'rov hakav*,
the הלכה Halacha, *halacha* is actually a half that amount, half of
a half, a quarter of a קב kav *kav* causes טומאת אהל
*tumat ohel*, כי איתא בהדיא במתניתין בפרק קמא דאהלות, פרק שני דאהלות
*ki isa b'hedya b'matnisin b'perek kama de'oholos, perek sheni de'oholos*, אלו מטמאין
באהל *elu mitamin b'ohel*, וחשיב רוב העצמות *vechashiv rov ha'atzamos* הבא מרוב
מנין ומרוב בנין *haba merov minyan umerov binyan*. So here it's a
half and there it's a quarter. מכל מקום *mikol makom* הלכה Halacha
הוא *halacha hu* שאין הנזיר מגלח megale'ach *she'ein hanazir megalei'ach* אלא על
חצי קב chatzi kav. *ella al chatzi kav*. Okay? That's the הלכה
Halachah, *halacha*. Okay. And then he dismisses another possibility. Meaning, there are
some cases they seem, they'll seem trivial because it's okay, fine, there's
a difference. A quarter of a קב kav *kav*, טומאת אהל *tumat
ohel*. A half of a קב kav *kav*, until you're מגלח megale'ach
*megalei'ach*. But there are a few cases that cause טומאת מת tumat
meis. דאורייתא *tumat meit de'oraisa* and nevertheless we have a tradition do
not let a נזיר Nazir *nazir* מגלח *megalei'ach*, you know, unless, you
know, are not נזיר מגלח nazir megaleach *nazir megalei'ach* and here it's
a question about a quarter of a קב kav *kav* versus a
half, we'll see some others which have some greater relevance. Okay? So
a half קב kav *kav* of bones, and as תוספות Tosafos *Tosafot*
says told us which come from רוב מנין rov minyan, *rov minyan*
or רוב בנין rov binyan, *rov binyan*.
Is he now allowed to be מטמא metamei?
*mitamei* himself? It might not be... No, it's...
Yeah, it could be, could be that it's not the לאו *lav*
either. By the כהן kohen *kohen* we say אין כהן Kohen מוזהר
עליו *ein kohen muzhar alav*.
Okay? So a כהן *kohen* can actually be מטמא metamei, *mitamei*?
Yes, correct, technically speaking. Okay, this is באהל *b'ohel*. This is באהל
*b'ohel*, okay? ועל חצי לוג דם *ve'al chatzi log dam* and on
a half a לוג *log* of blood. Now that's another good example
because if you remember at the end of yesterday we said רביעית
revi'it דם *revi'is dam* is מטמא metameh באהל *mitamei b'ohel*. So here
again רביעית דם *revi'is dam* is מטמא metameh באהל *mitamei b'ohel* from
a dead person, yes, but you need twice that amount in order
for the נזיר nazir *nazir* to be מגלח *megalei'ach*. So for the
bones and the blood when it comes to טומאת אהל *tumat ohel*,
you need twice the minimum amount for a נזיר nazir, *nazir* to
be מגלח *megalei'ach*. So that is, now what type of ways do
these conduct טומאה Tuma *tuma* and a נזיר nazir, *nazir* will be
מגלח *megalei'ach*? ועל מגען ועל משאן ועל אהילן *ve'al maga'an ve'al masa'an
ve'al ahilan*, touching them, carrying them, or being מאהיל *ma'ahil*, tenting over
them or having them tent over you or being under the same
rooftop, אהל *ohel*. So those, that list is all types of טומאה
Tuma *tuma*. Now here is the following list of things that cause
טומאת מת tumat meis, *tumat meit* not through אהל *ohel* but through
contact. ועל עצם כשעורה *ve'al etzem k'se'ora*, even a tiny little piece
of bone as small as a barley bean, what do they call
it, seed, is it seed? What is it called? A barley something,
grain. Okay. על מגעו ועל משאו *al maga'o ve'al masa'o*, touching and
carrying it. Okay? So here's that's something which causes טומאה Tuma *tuma*,
most of the things if they cause טומאה tumah. *tuma* by contact,
cause טומאה tumah באהל *tuma b'ohel*. Okay? But the basic one major
difference is bones. Bones as we just saw, you need either the
skull or the spinal cord or the רוב מנין rov minyan *rov
minyan* or the רוב בנין rov binyan, *rov binyan* or a certain
quantity that comes from those amounts, that's for טומאת אהל *tumat ohel*.
But for touch, even a tiny little chip of bone the size
of a grain of barley. Okay? And therefore that causes טומאת מת
tumat meis. *tumat meit* and therefore a נזיר nazir. *nazir* will shave.
על אלו הנזיר מגלח *al elu hanazir megalei'ach*, for these a נזיר
nazir *nazir* will shave his head, ומזה בשלישי ובשביעי *umazer bashlishi uvashevi'i*,
sprinkle the ashes on days three and seven, סותר את הקודמין *soter
es hakodmin*, it will destroy the earlier days, ואינו מתחיל למנות אלא
עד שייטהר *ve'eino mas'chil limnos ella ad sheyitaher*, right, and he, no,
for טומאה tumah. *tuma* all the earlier days. You're thinking about shaving.
But for טומאה tumah *tuma* all the earlier days and he does
not begin counting again אלא עד שייטהר מביא את קרבנותיו *ella ad
sheyitaher meivi es korbonosav* until he becomes טהור tahor. *tahor* and brings
the קרבנות *korbonos* the next day and then starts, starts, which is
interesting that he starts counting the next day, does he start the
day he delays bringing the קרבנות *korbonos*? We can worry about that
later. But basically this is a list of the minimum sizes of
the body and parts of the body that cause טומאת מת tumos
mess *tumat meit* and almost everything is the same minimum for אהל
*ohel* and other things with the exception of bones. Bones, a tiny
bit of bone causes טומאה tumah *tuma* by touch but you need
a much more significant amount to cause טומאת אהל *tumat ohel*. Okay?
And again that there are two things we identified so far that
cause טומאת מת tumas meis? *tumat meit* that a נזיר *nazir* is
not מגלח *megalei'ach* and that is less than a half קב *kav*
of עצמות *atzamos* and less than a half לוג *log* of blood.
That once it's a quarter of a, half of that amount it
causes טומאת מת tumas meis *tumat meit* but only with that amount
is a נזיר מגלח nazir megaleach. *nazir megalei'ach*. Okay, let's take a
look. The first list was טומאת אוהל, tumat ohel yes, yes, not
so you don't have to infer it, the first list ended with
על מגען ועל משאן ועל אהילן. al mag'an v'al masa'an v'al ohilan.
So you have one big list which tells you everything on this
list causes טומאה tumah through touch, carrying, and אוהל, Ohel, and then
there's one thing that only causes טומאה tumah through touch and not
through אוהל Ohel and that's a chip of bone, okay, that's exactly
what the משנה's Mishna doing, it's constructing two lists and telling you
the first list is everything, the second list is just through touch
and carrying, not through אוהל. Ohel. Yes?
Am I reading the משנה Mishna correctly that everything here as a
source of טומאה tumah comes from a מת Met except for אבר
מן החי? Ever min hachai?
Correct, yes, that is correct.
So there's a glaring,
yes, and that's why I made that point. Let's take a look
at the גמרא. Gemara. תנו רבנן: Tenu Rabbanan: אחר פטירתו של רבי
מאיר, achar ptirato she' Rabbi Meir, after Rabbi Meir passed away, אמר
להם רבי יהודה לתלמידיו, amar lahem Rabbi Yehuda l'talmidav, Rabbi Yehuda said
to his students: אל יכנסו תלמידי רבי מאיר לכאן, Al yikansu talmidei
Rabbi Meir l'chan, don't let Rabbi Meir's students into our בית מדרש,
Beit Midrash, מפני שקנתרין הם mipnei she'kantarin hem
because they are troublemakers, ולא ללמוד תורה הן באין, v'lo lilmod Torah
hen ba'in,
they don't have a sincere desire to learn תורה, Torah, אלא לקפחני
בהלכות הן באין, ella l'kapechani bahalachot hen ba'in,
they're trying to just like annoy me with their matters of הלכה,
Halachah, meaning they're trying to show how brilliant they are, right? We've
all had students like that, they want to, maybe they don't want
to דוקא dafka annoy the teacher but they always often manage to
do that, and they're really just interested in the whole thing as
an intellectual exercise and the mind games and they're not really coming
to like just for the sake of learning תורה Torah and getting
to the הלכה Halachah, and getting to the answer. Okay, so don't
let them in the בית מדרש. Beit Midrash. Okay, so דחק סומכוס
ונכנס. dachak Sumchus v'nichnas.
So Sumchus forced his way in and he got into the בית
מדרש, Beit Midrash, okay, and Sumchus was one of the תלמידי מובהקים
רבי מאיר. talmidei muvhakim Rabbi Meir. אמר להם, Amar lahem, so they
were learning this משנה Mishna presumably, and presumably this is Rabbi Yehuda
said, you know, a נזיר is מגלח על כזית מן המת, al
kezayit min hamet, and Sumchus said כך שנא לי רבי מאיר, kach
shani li Rabbi Meir, when Rabbi Meir taught me this משנה, Mishna,
here's how he taught it to me: על אלו טומאת הנזיר מגלח
על המת ועל כזית מן המת. al elu tumat hanazir megale'ach al
hamet v'al kezayit min hamet.
So he didn't just say על כזית מן המת, al kezayit min
hamet, I'm explaining this based on the later discussion, it seems like
this is the context. He said on a מת Met and on
a כזית מן המת. kezayit min hamet. כעס רבי יהודה Ka'as Rabbi
Yehuda ואמר להם, v'amar lahem,
Rabbi Yehuda got angry and he said to his students: לא כך
אמרתי לכם? Lo kach amarti lachem?
Didn't I tell you this? אל יכנסו תלמידי רבי מאיר לכאן, Al
yikansu talmidei Rabbi Meir l'chan,
don't let Rabbi Meir's students into the בית מדרש, Beit Midrash, מפני
שקנתרין הם, mipnei she'kantarin hem,
they're troublemakers. על כזית מן המת מגלח על המת לא כל שכן?
al kezayit min hamet megale'ach al hamet lo kol sheken? If you're
מגלח on a כזית מן המת, kezayit min hamet, why do you
have to say על המת? al hamet? Now this is very
bizarre, okay, because alright, so it's a little bit of a little
extra phrase, this means you're a troublemaker? Now maybe the troublemaker is
because he's giving me a hard time. I said כזית מן המת
kezayit min hamet and he's challenging me to say oh you can't
just say כזית מן המת, kezayit min hamet, you have to first
say על המת. al hamet. It's like why is that important? I
mean it's impressive, okay, so maybe the troublemaker is not that Rabbi
Meir taught על כזית מן המת al kezayit min hamet but the
insistence on saying that first, like what's the point?
I know it's annoying but I'm saying if he just said oh
my version was this, like okay whatever, but if he's making himself
annoying about that, right? He's saying you can't just say כזית מן
המת, kezayit min hamet, you have to say על המת על כזית
מן המת. al hamet al kezayit min hamet. So what are you
doing? You're just you know you're just making trouble like it's implicit,
why what difference does it make? Okay, now אמר רבי יוסי, amar
Rabbi Yosi, so said רבי יוסי: Rabbi Yosi: No, we're not done,
read the next line. אמר רבי יוסי, amar Rabbi Yosi, so said
Rabbi Yosi: יאמרו מאיר שכב, Yomru Meir shakav,
they'll say Meir passed away,
יהודה כעס, Yehuda ka'as, Yehuda got angry, יוסי שתק, Yosi shatach, and
I was silent? תורה מה תהא עליה? Torah mah tehei aleha? What
will be about תורה? Torah? Like you know Rabbi Meir's תורה Torah
is being sort of dismissed in his death? I have to come
to defend, even though I'm a student of Rabbi Yehuda or a
colleague of Rabbi Yehuda, whatever, you know I have to come and
defend Rabbi Meir's honor because to defend his תורה. Torah. אמר רבי
יוסי: Amar Rabbi Yosi: לא נצרכה אלא מת שאין עליו כזית בשר.
Lo nitzrecha ella met she'ein alav kezayit basar.
Now here's what you need it for. Let's imagine you have a
dead body that you have the entire body but there's no flesh
left, it's all just bones. So that's why you need to say
על המת. al hamet. Now that's a difficult answer because then you
also that's implicit in the bone issue, right? Because we also mentioned
a certain amount of bones, right? So the גמרא Gemara said: ועדיין
יאמר על אבר ממנו מגלח על כולו לא כל שכן? V'adayin yomar
al ever mimenu megale'ach al kulo lo kol sheken?
Okay,
but so what? If even for one limb you shave, of course
for the whole body? You didn't really answer the question why do
you need to
say
on the
whole body? אלא כי דאמר רבי יוחנן, Ella k'd'amar Rabbi Yochanan, like
Rabbi Yochanan taught: לא נצרכה אלא נפל שלא נתקשרו אבריו בגידים. Lo
nitzrecha ella nefel shelo nitkashu evarav begidim. We're talking
about a- about a stillbirth that the- the sinews did not yet
develop. develop, and because there are no גידין, gidin, we don't know
this yet, but I'm telling you, it does not have the idea
of an איבר eiver does not apply. Okay. Now, of
course the
infant has bones, it has
flesh apparently, but it doesn't have some of the sinews have not
developed. Again, I don't know, I'm not an embryologist, I can't attest
to this. Anyway, but apparently that you don't have the טומאת איבר
tumat eiver if it doesn't have גידין, gidin, okay? So that's a
case where you could have a whole מת meis and if it's
a very small, very tiny embryo, it doesn't have a כזית בשר.
kezayis basar. Okay. Now, what about the idea of רוב מנין, rov
minyan רוב בנין, rov binyan you know, שדרה, shidra, גולגולת? gulgoles? Maybe
that doesn't apply when it's such a, I don't know, when does
it even develop a skeletal structure? Must develop it early though, right?
Fairly early. Yeah. I don't know. Anyway, it's not exactly clear to
me why you don't have the idea of the שדרה shidra and
גולגולת, gulgoles, but maybe there's some assumption also that if it's that
small, that doesn't apply. Okay. So הכא נמי hacha nami by נפל
שלא נתקשרו איבריו בגידין, nefel shelo nitkashru evarav begidin,
that's the case where you have it where you can have a
whole מת meis that doesn't fall into any of those other categories.
רבא אמר, Rava amar, לא נצרכה אלא לרוב בניינו ולרוב מניינו שאין
בהן רובע עצמות. lo nitzrecha ela lerov binyano ulerov minyano she-ein bahen
rova atzamot. Okay, no, basically we can be talking about you have
the skeletal structure, so you have רוב מנין rov minyan and רוב
בנין, rov binyan... but what happens? Again, if it's a very small
corpse and you can have רוב מנין rov minyan and רוב בנין
rov binyan, and you don't have the minimum quantity. You don't have
the רובע עצמות. rova atzamot. Interesting he mentions רובע rova as opposed
to the חצי קב. chatzi kav. Okay, that's probably a little לאו
דוקא lav davka because the normal again טומאת אוהל tumat ohel. is
רובע rova even though here we're talking about נזיר מגלח so it's
a חצי קב. chatzi kav. So he says you could have a
case where you have no flesh, you just have the skeleton,
but it's a very small skeleton. So even though it's רוב מנין
rov minyan and רוב בנין... rov binyan. Now this is interesting, right,
because we might have imagined if you really have רוב מנין rov
minyan and רוב בנין, rov binyan it's not measured by quantity. Now
we see that that gets back to the תוספות Tosafos I read
to you, that it's the intersection of these two. Right, you need
a half of a... a quarter of a קב or a half
of a קב for רוב מנין rov minyan or רוב בנין. rov
binyan, Even if you had an entire רוב מנין rov minyan and
רוב בנין rov binyan by itself, uncrushed, whole, the entire thing by
itself, if it were not... if it did not have the minimum
volume, it would not cause טומאת אוהל. So that's important for an...
well no, but apparently the same is true in general for טומאת
מת. tumas meis, The only difference of a נזיר is a רובע
rova versus a חצי קב. Okay, but basically this is important, that
it's not just רוב מנין rov minyan and רוב בנין, rov binyan
it's רוב מנין rov minyan and רוב בנין that also is a
quarter of a קב for טומאת מת, tumas meis, a half of
a קב for נזיר מגלח. But again, the interesting thing it's ignoring
is the שדרה shidra and the גולגולת. gulgoles.
No, איבר. eiver. And we said איבר eiver needs flesh.
No idea of בריה beriah by טומאת מת. tumat meit Okay, so
basically you don't have איבר eiver because you don't have flesh. You
don't have flesh because you don't have flesh. You don't have רוב
מנין and רוב בנין because even though you do, you don't have
a רובע קב עצמות rova kav atzamot or half of a קב
really is what you need for a נזיר, so you need רוב
מנין plus that quantity. The thing that's not being addressed is the
שדרה shidra and the גולגולת gulgoles and I don't know what the
answer to that is. Yes, a נפל... nefel... died or...
No, a נפל nefel
is a stillborn or miscarriage, yeah. Yeah, it could even be as
early as like, you know, the fortieth day, which could be how
it could be very undeveloped.
Okay, but again, it's what's not being explored here is why these
are exceptions to a שדרה shidra and גולגולת. gulgoles. I want to
say two things about this context about this. It is interesting, it's
hard to talk about this, right? It's sort of so
objectifying and impersonal talking about these parts of a dead body. It's
interesting in this context that it starts with the story of talking
about death and talking about death in a much more sort of
euphemistic way, in a much more respectful way, right? It says פטירה,
petirah, which literally means he
left, right? He took his leave of us, right? And then it
says אמר רבי יוסי יאמר מי ששכב, amar Rabi Yosi yomar mi
she-shachav, which literally meant he went to lie down, right? So both
of those are just more, I think, dignified, don't objectify this as
body parts when somebody dies, and also I think suggest also that
sense about going to a different world, going to a different place.
He takes his leave of us, you know, and there's still the
soul that lives on and so on. So it's interesting the different
terminologies of death that are introduced here. The other thing though is
that when this exact exchange also appears in קידושין, Kiddushin, and there
it makes a lot more sense for two reasons, A) literary and
B) why it's so annoying. The משנה Mishnah in קידושין Kiddushin talks
about what types of objects a man can use to marry a
woman, and are they considered איסור הנאה issur hana'ah or not. So
it says that a כהן can
marry a woman by giving her the meat of קדשי קדשים, kodshei
kodashim, like of a חטאת, chatas, you know, that it has value.
I mean, she can't eat it, but you know, it has value,
she could sell it back to other כהנים. kohanim. Okay, so that's
what it says. Okay, בשר קדשי קדשים. basar kodshei kodashim. And apparently
that was a משנה Mishnah of רבי מאיר. Rabi Meir. So our
משנה Mishnah turns out to have been a משנה Mishnah of רבי
מאיר. Rabi Meir. So the גמרא Gemara there starts by the same
story. After רבי Rebbi died, רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehudah said don't let
any of those students whatever get in here. דחק סומכוס ונכנס לשם.
dachak Sumchus v'nichnas l'sham. סומכוס Sumchus forced his way in and he
said, here's what רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir told me, a person can
be מקדש mekadesh a wife with בשר קדשי קדשים. basar Kodshei Kodashim.
So then רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehudah
got upset and he says, like the same thing, didn't I tell
you don't let רבי מאיר's Rabbi Meir students in? He says, what
is a woman doing in the עזרה Azarah in the בית המקדש
Beis HaMikdash that they're doing a קידושין Kiddushin ceremony right there in
the עזרה? Azarah? So there you understand it's like, you understand what
bothered him more, it's like he said this isn't like real הלכה,
Halachah, these are like mind games, right? So we want to talk
about like practical הלכה, halacha you just want to explore interesting theoretical
absurd types of ideas. So you a little bit more understand what
bothers him. But what's particularly cute about that גמרא Gemara is then
the גמרא Gemara gives a whole series of answers about how a
woman could be in the עזרה. Azarah. By the way, it's interesting
because a woman is not not allowed in the עזרה, Azarah, as
תוספות Tosafos, demonstrates. So the question is not so much that she's
not allowed, but it would be as תוספות Tosafot either unusual for
her to be there for not the purpose of bringing a קרבן,
korban, or you know inappropriate for her to be there and to
be doing an act of קידושין Kiddushin although then it's not so
much about the woman, it's about doing an act of קידושין Kiddushin
in the עזרה. Azarah. But anyway, תוספות Tosafot says it's not that
she's not allowed, but it would not happen, you know, would not
be expected and it would not be usual for her to do
הלכה, halacha right right.
Anyway but it's like an absurd scenario is what's being said, not
that it's forbidden. Anyway, so the גמרא Gemara has a series of
answers. So one answer is, well, maybe the כהן is giving it
to her father and he's marrying off his daughter, or maybe she
made a שליח shliach and he's accepting it for her in the
עזרה. Azarah. And then the final answer was, the final answer was,
דחקה ונכנסה מאי, dachakah v'nichnesah mai,
maybe she just forced her way into the עזרה, Azarah, which plays
off on the beginning of the story which is סומכוס Sumchus was
דחק ונכנס. dachak v'nichnas. So it seems there that
this literary construct really comes from that case, both why he got
upset and also the whole דחק ונכנס, dachak v'nichnas, you know, and
the absurdity of the scenarios really sort of shows like what this
means that רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir they're like playing these mind games
and they're not just coming for
הלכה, halacha?
yes. Which סוגיא sugya is this?
It's נב עמוד ב. nun beis amud beis. In מה?
mah? קידושין. Kiddushin. נב? nun beis? Yeah. Okay. Second thing you see,
nothing's changed, the Jews, you could rent the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash
for a wedding. Exactly. Right.
Look at the first רש״י Rashi on the גמרא Gemara here, right
at the top there, גץ
צורא.
getz tzora.
It's like cognitive terror, like the terror of...
Really? Oh that's interesting. Okay. Yes. רבי דב Rabbi Dov made a
nice point.
מה דההיא mah d'hahi מאיר שכב יהודה כעס יוסי שתק Meir shachav
Yehudah kaas Yossi shatak is really saying that they've gotten too personal
about it, you know, everybody's thinking what will so-and-so say that the
personalities are what's important, more important than the actual what they're doing.
Ah, that's very nice. שקויח. sh'koach. Right, that's very very nice. שקויח.
sh'koach. Everybody hear the point that דוב Dov made? He said the
point about מאיר שכב יהודה כעס יוסי שתק Meir shachav Yehudah kaas
Yossi shatak is that it will all lead to a discussion about
the people and the personalities and we're forgetting the תורה Torah that's
being taught and it's really sort of a reorienting to the תורה
Torah which is really what's important about all of this. שקויח. sh'koach.
Okay now we go on. כזית מן המת כזית נצל. kezayis min
hamess kezayis netzel. So now we move, a כזית kezayis of the
corpse which is basically the flesh and a כזית kezayis of this
נצל netzel which is some type of dissolved and recongealed flesh, thank
you. So it says, ואיזהו נצל? v'eizehu netzel? What is this נצל?
netzel? בשר המת שקרש. basar hamess shekarash. So the flesh of a
dead body that has congealed, but obviously first had liquefied and then
it congealed.
ומוהל שהרתיח. u'mohel she'hirtiach. And also some type of a juices, I
can't say it any other way, that ran off from the flesh
that then were like boiled and congealed. Now the question is why
does it say boiled? So I'll get back to that in a
minute, but the גמרא Gemara is going to focus on the first
phrase. Let's take a look.
Okay.
So those are two versions of נצל. netzel. So one it seems
like it just naturally congeals and the other maybe it congealed through
boiling, one maybe more was flesh that had liquefied, the other more
just the juices themselves that ran off. היכי דמי? Heichi dami? Now
what's the case? It starts with the issue about the בשר. basar.
אילימא דלא ידיענא דדידיה הוא, Ilima d'lo yadiana d'didei hu, if we
don't know that this we have this congealed thing and we don't
know where it came from, did it come from the body or
not? כי קרש מאי הוי? Ki karash mai havay? So solidified meaning
doesn't mean anything. Now תוספות' Tosafot point about this issue, not תוספות,
Tosafot the גמרא's Gemara דדידיה הוא d'didei hu is it his? I
mean who else's? We'll see in a minute in the גמרא Gemara
it means did it come from the flesh or maybe it came
from other types of liquids that are running off the body, like
for example the spit or the or the mucus or other types
of liquids that are not the flesh. So if we don't know
if it's congealed flesh then congealing shouldn't tell us anything.
And these liquids are not מטמא?
metameh Those liquids are not מטמא, certainly not טומאת מת met, or
whatever, they might be indirect because they are in contact with the
dead but they're not the. themselves the dead. Okay, so אלא דידעינן
דדידהו. ela diadinan dedidaihu. So we know that it was the flesh
that had dissolved and recongealed. אף על גב דלא קריש. af al
gav d'lo karish. So he needs it to congeal, meaning now you
could have said, why not? Meaning who knows? Maybe if it's all
in liquid form, you know, I don't know what these הלכות halachos
are, maybe if it's in liquid form that's not considered flesh, maybe
it has to be in solid form. But the Gemara takes it
for granted that it is, so even if it was in dissolved
form, once it was actually coming from the flesh, it should cause
the same טומאה. tumah? So let's see what the Gemara's answer is.
The Gemara says אמר רבי ירמיה בסתם. amar Rabbi Yirmiyah bistam. We
don't know what the nature of this congealed liquid is. Okay, אי
קרש, ei karash, I mean obviously it came from the body, אי
קרש ei karash if it congealed, מוהל הוא, mohel hu, so then
we know that it is juices from the flesh and therefore it
represents the flesh and that's why it's מטמא in an amount of
a כזית. kezayis. לא קרש lo karash if it doesn't congeal, then
דילמא כיחו וניעו הוא, dilma keicho venieio hu, maybe it's his spit
and it's mucus and therefore we don't know. So basically the Gemara,
which is מחדש mechadesh that you don't really need it to congeal,
basically it doesn't matter what form it's in, but dissolved flesh or
the juices that run off of the flesh are מטמא like the
flesh itself, and this issue of congealing is only to determine what
its identity is. Tosafos says that's the same about the second point
about this here הירתיח, hirtiyach, boiling, whatever that means. So if you
take a look at Tosafos, Tosafos says אמר רבי ירמיה בסתם. amar
Rabbi Yirmiyah bistam. So he says כלומר דידעינן דבא מזה המת. klomar
dyadinan deba mizeh hamais. We know it came from the
body, אבל לא ידעינן מוהל זה מבשרו או מכיחו וניעו. aval lo
yadinan mohel zeh mibasaro o mikeicho venieio. We don't know what the
source of this liquid was from the body. קרש ודאי מוהל הוא
הבא מבשר המת karash vadai mohel hu haba mibasar hamais if it
congeals then it's definitely like from the juices of the flesh or
from a dissolved flesh or the juices of the flesh. ואילו לא
קרש כיחו וניעו הוא. ve'ilu lo karash keicho venieio hu. And then
he says והכי נמי יש לפרש גבי הירתיח דלא ידעינן. ve'hachi nami
yesh lefaresh gabei hirtiyach d'lo yadinan. This could be, the Gemara never
deals with the הירתיח hirtiyach case, but Tosafos says we'll assume the
same. Okay, that you basically have some juices that then, and you
don't know what type of, what they are, whether they're from the
flesh or elsewhere or from the mucus. וכי הירתיח והדר רתח ודאי
מוהל הבא מהמת הוא vechi hirtiyach vehadar rasach vadai mohel haba mehamais
hu and if it gets boiled and it starts, I don't know,
you know, like bubbling or whatever, then you know that it's from
the flesh. וזהו נצל. vezehu netzel. לא הירתיח כיחו וניעו הוא. lo
hirtiyach keicho venieio hu. I have to tell you I don't really
understand that. כיחו keicho is like the spit, the phlegm, yeah. But
I have to tell you that I don't really understand that because
why can't, I mean any liquid you could boil. It's one thing
to say it's not able to congeal by itself, I don't get
the exact boiling as a test of what its nature is. But
Tosafos anyway tries to fit that into the same pattern of the
Gemara. So the basic upshot about this is that if it's juices
from the flesh, then and we know what its identity is, then
it's also מטמא like the flesh itself. Okay. So now the Gemara
goes on, a little less graphic now. בעי מיניה אביי מרבא. ba'ei
minei Abaye meRava. Abaye asked Rava. I mean not so much less
graphic, but anyway. יש נצל לבהמה או אין נצל לבהמה. yeish netzel
l'beheimah o ein netzel l'beheimah.
This idea that juices from the flesh count like the flesh itself,
does this apply to other areas of טומאה tumah, in addition to
טומאת מת? met, Maybe it's a matter of definition of flesh and
therefore we could apply it in other areas outside of טומאת מת
met like טומאת נבילה. tumas neveilah. Okay? If you have a כזית
kezayis of a dead animal corpse of the flesh, it causes טומאה.
tumah, Not טומאת מת, it's not relevant for a נזיר, we're no
longer dealing with a נזיר. A נזיר can touch dead animal
carcasses, fine. That's not our issue. Our issue is does it cause
טומאה tumah, if it's not the actual flesh but it's the juices
from the flesh, if it's liquefied or it's the juices that ran
off. Okay? יש נצל לבהמה או אין נצל לבהמה. yeish netzel l'beheimah
o ein netzel l'beheimah. מי אמרינן, mi amrinan, do we say גמירי
נצל דאתי מאדם, gemiri netzel d'asi me'adam, just for the נצל netzel
that comes from a human? So it's a הלכה in טומאת מת,
it's not a general definition of flesh. אבל דאתי מבהמה לא, aval
d'asi mibeheimah lo, but it wouldn't apply to like
carcasses of animals. או דילמא, o dilma, or do we say לא
שנא, lo shena, it won't matter, then it also applies to carcasses
of animals? It generally it's a statement that the juices from the
flesh count as the flesh. Okay. So the Gemara says like this,
now this question is really moot depending on another question. הניחא למאן
דאמר טומאה חמורה עד לגר וטומאה קלה עד לכלב שפיר. hanicha leman
d'amar tumah chamurah ad lager vetumah kalah ad lekelev shapir. If you
say weighty טומאה tumah is measured by being until the threshold of
a stranger and the light טומאה tumah by the dog, then it
makes sense. Well, that was a clear enough phrase. Okay. So what
does that mean? What it means is the following.
The Gemara can sometimes pack a lot into a little phrase. So
it means the following: when it speaks about the
טומאה tumah of a carcass, it says לגר אשר בשעריך תתננה ואכלה.
lager asher bish'arecha titnenah ve'achalah. You can't eat this נבילה, neveilah, give
it to the גר, ger, to the stranger in your land, and
let him eat this נבילה. neveilah. You as a Jew cannot eat
this נבילה. neveilah. Okay. And from there we learn הראוי לגר קרוי
נבילה ושאינו ראוי לגר אינו קרוי נבילה, haraui lager karuy neveilah veshe'eino
raui lager eino karuy neveilah, that it's only considered a נבילה neveilah
if it's edible. גר ger we don't think that non-Jews have different
eating patterns than Jews or taste buds, but that's the example in
the Torah. So if it’s fit for human consumption, it’s called a
נבלה, neveila, not for human consumption, it’s not called a נבלה. neveila.
Now that has relevance in laws of טומאה וטהרה tumah v’taharah when
something becomes not fit for eating human consumption, does it lose its
status as forbidden food? And it also can be relevant for laws
of טומאה tumah when it becomes not fit for human consumption, does
it stop being a source of טומאה? tumah So that’s when it
says טומאה חמורה עד לגר tumah chamura ad leger means weighty טומאה,
tumah, the carcass of an animal that is an אב av and
a source of טומאה, tumah it will stop having that power once
it is no longer fit for being eaten by a human being.
Now that’s strange because a lot of טומאות tumot have nothing to
do with food, with being food, right? A corpse of a human
being, זב, zav, נדה, niddah, מצורע, metzora, like most אבות הטומאות avot
hatumot are not because of their identity as food. Now you could
still say if it’s no longer fit for consumption it means that
somehow it’s transformed significantly enough, but it’s still strange that we use
as the measuring stick its edibility. But that would be the idea
that at least when it comes to
טומאת נבלה, tumat neveila, which is a carcass of an animal which
would be eaten usually and nevertheless is a source of טומאה, tuma
that there it loses that status once it’s no longer fit for
human consumption. That’s טומאה חמורה עד לגר. tumah chamura ad leger. Now
טומאה קלה עד לכלב, tumah kala ad lekelev, what does that mean?
Not when it’s an אב הטומאה, av hatumah, but when something gets
טומאה tumah. from something else. What types of things can conduct טומאה
tumah from other things? Humans, vessels, and anybody know the third category?
Food. So food that conducts טומאה tumah from elsewhere, what is the
minimum standard of food to define it as food that it conducts
טומאה tumah when it touches something else? Is it ראוי לאכילת אדם
raui l’achilat adam or ראוי לאכילת כלב? raui l’achilat kelev? These phrases
might be familiar to you with הלכות פסח, hilchot Pesach, these are
broader questions about and different areas might have different definitions of what
defines something as food. Okay, so if טומאה חמורה עד לגר tumah
chamura ad leger means it stops being a נבלה neveila when it’s
no longer fit for human consumption and having the טומאת נבלה, tumat
neveila, טומאה קלה עד לכלב tumah kala ad lekelev is really a
parenthetical statement completely irrelevant to us but it’s part of the phrase
so the whole phrase was quoted and means when it comes to
something being food to conduct טומאה tumah, elsewhere it might be enough
that it’s fit for being eaten by dogs. But the weight of
being a source of טומאה, tumah? particularly when you’re talking about something
like a נבלה, neveila, right, then it’s only if it is fit
for human consumption. Again it’s ironic because most טומאות tumot have nothing
to do with their edibility, but at least by נבלה neveila we’re
saying until it’s fit for human consumption. So if you say that,
then he says the question is moot. Why is the question moot?
Because these juices that run off the flesh, he’s assuming, are not
fit for human consumption, right? Which is funny because if you think
about when you cut into your steak and the juices run off
and whatever, you know, people mop it up with their bread. I’m
right talking to some vegans here?
It’s amazing right, the connection.
Yes, but we are talking about dead animals. Okay, I do realize,
I’m sorry for the putrefaction of flesh. Right, so the difference might
be
exactly, exactly. This might not be right
just the meat on your plate, right, it is as the body
decomposes. So the assumption is that the juices that run off from
the flesh as the body decomposes are not fit for human consumption
and therefore it says whether you say it has a status of
the flesh or not, it’s a moot point because when we’re dealing
with the טומאה of נבלה, neveila, right, other טומאות tumot are not
about fit for consumption, טומאת מת is not about fit, but when
we’re dealing with נבלה neveila it’s about fit for consumption. So therefore
it’s really a moot question
whether the liquids have a status of flesh. They’re not fit for
human consumption, end of story. Okay, so let’s read that again. הניחא
למאן דאמר טומאה חמורה עד לגר, Hania leman de’amar tumah chamura ad
leger, when it comes to the weighty, the נבלה, neveila, it has
to be fit for human consumption. טומאה קלה עד לכלב, Tumah kala
ad lekelev, other types of food טומאות, tumot, fit for dogs. So
that’s parenthetical. שפיר, Shapir, then
that makes sense, meaning it’s a moot point because these juices are
not fit for human consumption, end of story. אלא למאן דאמר טומאה
חמורה עד לכלב, Ella leman de’amar tumah chamura ad lekelev,
but according to the approach that even for a נבלה neveila it
doesn’t have to be human consumption, it only has to be consumable
by a dog. Okay, again, still we’re still using a definition of
food by נבלה neveila that we don’t use by other טומאות, tumot,
but by a dog is enough. So if that’s true, so that’s
then that’s my question. These juices presumably are edible by a dog.
Do they have a status of meat or not? Okay, that’s the
question. Right. Right. So do we say אלא למאן דאמר טומאה חמורה
עד לכלב מאי איכא למימר, ella leman de’amar tumah chamura ad lekelev
mai ika lemeimar,
what’s the story? תא שמע, Ta shema, come and hear. המחהו באור
טמא בחמה טהור. Himchehu ba’or tamei bachama tahor.
You have this נבלה neveila and you go ahead and dissolve it
over a fire. You liquefy it over a fire. Then it is
טמא. tamei. If however you let it rot and liquefy
When you leave it rot by leaving it out in the sun,
presumably it becomes putrefied and completely unfit for eating. When you put
it out on the fire, presumably it's not getting putrefied. Okay, so
ואי סלקא דעתך עד לכלב, ve'i salka daitach ad lekelev, and if
you say that something it loses its טומאה remains טמא tamei as
long as it's fit, נבילה neveila remains טמא tamei as long as
it's fit for a dog, אפילו בחמה נמי. afillu bechama nami.
So it assumes that even in the sun it should remain fit
for a dog. So this doesn't actually prove answer our question. All
that's being demonstrated by this is that presumably the difference here, it's
assuming that something that's liquefied by being left in the sun is
fit for a dog, okay, and it's saying that it's טהור. tahor.
So it proves one way or another the liquids are טהור. tahor,
Either because you need ראוי לאדם ra'ui le'adam or because the liquids
aren't defined as the meat. Okay, but if the liquids when left
out in the sun is טהור, tahor so the גמרא Gemara's assuming
you see you need ראוי לאדם, ra'ui le'adam, because if ראוי לכלב
ra'ui lekelev was enough and it was considered meat even when it
liquefied, it should be טמא. tamei. So the גמרא Gemara says no.
The גמרא Gemara says
ואי סלקא דעתך לכלב אפילו בחמה נמי. ve'i salka daitach lekelev afillu
bechama nami. גמרא Gemara says no. אימת מתחלי? Eimat matchilei?
No, no, no, says the גמרא, Gemara, no. When you leave it
out on the sun, when does it sort of liquefy? בתר דאסטרח,
Basar de'astrich,
after it putrefies. So בחמה כיון דאסטרח הוי ליה עפר. bechama kivan
de'astrich havei lei afar. If you leave it on the sun, after
it's putrefied, it's spoiled, it's like dust, meaning it's not even ראוי
לכלב. ra'ui lekelev. Okay, and that thankfully is the end of that
discussion. Okay, so the question was, is the liquefied flesh of an
animal considered טומאת נבילה, tumas neveila, meat for טומאת נבילה? tumas neveila?
In order to answer that question we would have to assume you
don't need ראוי לאדם, ra'ui le'adam, and we don't know the answer
whether or not you need ראוי לאדם. ra'ui le'adam. And the one
משנה, Mishna, actually תוספתא Tosefta that somehow is relevant and talks about
liquefied, it could be seen as saying it's טהור tahor because it's
not ראוי לאדם, ra'ui le'adam,
but then because that's what happens when you leave it out in
the sun. But the גמרא Gemara comes back and says no, that
might be טהור tahor. because it's not ראוי לכלב. ra'ui lekelev. And
maybe when it's when it's ראוי לכלב ra'ui lekelev and not ראוי
לאדם, ra'ui le'adam, maybe your question is still relevant. Okay, and we
in the end don't know the answer to that question. Now we
get to another one which is a lot more pleasant. Let's take
a look. תנן. Tenan. So we're going to introduce this next conversation
by starting with a משנה Mishna in מכשירין. Machshirin. Does that imply
the conclusion here that it is ראוי לאכילה?
ra'ui leachila? No, no, it does no, it just the conclusion is
that
if it's left out in the sun it's not ראוי לכלב. ra'ui
lekelev. And we don't really have a conclusion about what would be
about the הלכה if it were ראוי לכלב. ra'ui lekelev. Okay, now
we have a משנה. Mishna. כל הניצוק טהור. Kol hanitzok tahor. All
pouring things are טהור. tahor. Now does what it means is the
following. I have something טמא tamei here, you know, I don't know,
let's say about a carcass of a dead animal. And I'm pouring
water on the carcass. So water that hits the animal is טמא,
tamei, right? It's a ראשון rishon 'cause it's in contact with that.
What about the water that's still in my jug up here? Do
we say that it's all connected in one unit like if I
touch the animal with my with a stick, it wouldn't just be
the tip of the stick would be טמא, tamei, the whole stick
would be טמא. tamei. So how about this connection through being poured?
Does that make it one object or not? And the answer is
no, it's not one object. כל הניצוק טהור. Kol hanitzok tahor. It
doesn't mean the stuff that hit, but it means being in the
process of being poured, it remains טהור. tahor. Only the stuff that
actually touches is טמא, tamei, okay? It's not one object. חוץ Chutz
with the exception מדבש הזיפים midvash ha'ziphim from דבש dvash of זיפים
ziphim which is possibly a place or תוספות Tosafot says something else
about what it might mean. Oh, it just is a very thick
type of a honey. If I just refer to its thickness, okay,
which basically is a very, very thick honey. והצפיחית Ve'hatzapichit which תוספות
says could mean like the cakes of honey that come straight out
of the beehive. Those are so thick that they actually are considered
more like a solid. Now it's an interesting question. Somebody told me
that somebody once asked Rav Moshe about, you know, about like about
Jell-O. Is it a liquid or a solid? I think it was
appertaining to trying to remember what the question was. It might have
been like the minimum שיעור shiur for a ברכה אחרונה bracha achrona
or something. Do you go by כזית kezayit or a רביעית or
whatever? So he said, so he said, yeah, I can't figure that
one out either. So anyway, it's sort of like the liquid crystal
question. Okay, so anyway, so is it okay, so the really thick
honey, really thick honey is a solid. Now בית שמאי אומרים, Beit
Shammai omrim, or it's not a solid but it's enough that it's
seen as one object. בית שמאי אומרים אף המקפה של גריסין ושל
פול, Beit Shammai omrim af hamikpa shel gerisin veshel pol, even certain
types of oatmeal of of lentil is considered like really thick, and
therefore if you're pouring it onto let's say this carcass then the
whole thing becomes טמא, tamei, מפני שהיא סולדת לאחוריה, mipne shehi soledet
leachoreha, because it pulls back. What does it mean it pulls back?
It means that if you were to like stop the pouring, okay,
it wouldn't be if you're pouring... liquid and you turn up like
that, everything that's out of your cup is gonna fall to the
ground, right? But if you're turning something else that's like really thick
and it's, I guess viscous or whatever, if you pull it then
some of it stays back with you, it doesn't all go away.
So that shows that it's more connected. By the way the phrase
סולדת, soledet, which means to like retract backwards, is relevant for the
שיעור shiur of יד סולדת בו, yad soledet bo, right? which is
the, which is the, how hot the certain liquids have to be
to be considered cooking, etc. So you recoil, you touch it and
you sort of recoil back. Okay. So, by Rami Bar Chama, and
Rami Bar, that's the Mishnah. Now we're going to ask our question.
יש ניצוק לאוכלין או אין ניצוק לאוכלין. Yesh nitzok le'ochlin o ein
nitzok le'ochlin. Now you can obviously understand where this question is being
informed based on our Mishnah, but again let's start with it: is
there ניצוק, nitzok, is it when for foods. Let's say you took
something that started as a food, okay, and you liquefied it. All
right, you went ahead and you took, I mean you could either
do it I guess by cooking it or you took your chicken
and you put it in your food processor, vroom, and you made
it into some thick mass, some thick liquefied type of a food.
Okay, and then you poured it on a מת, okay, or on
a נבילה. neveila. Okay, what would be the הלכה? Would that be
considered to be connected or not connected? Okay. So I want to
point out the sound you made was an immersion blender and not
really a food processor. Okay. All right. מי אמינא? Mi amina? Do
we say, מי אמינא Mi amina משום דאית בהו רירי? mishum de'it
behu riri? והני לית בהו רירי? Vehani leit behu riri? The reason
for the things mentioned earlier, whether it is the honey for the
חכמים Chachamim or the oatmeal for רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, is because
they have רירי, riri, and רירין ririn are like tentacles. How do
they describe רירין? ririn? It's like things that actually, it's not just
thick, but it's like it adheres. It's like strings that pull back.
Thick strings that screen, okay, fine. That's a good one-word for it.
Okay. I like, I like tentacles. That's good. Anyway. Okay. Anyway. Is
that why, משום דאית בהו רירין, mishum de'it behu ririn, okay, והני
לית בהו רירין? vehani leit behu ririn? This even though it's like
really, really thick, your, your mash, your liquid, your whatever, your pulverized
chicken, it doesn't have any of these like sticky components. Right. או
דלמא משום דסמיכי? O dilma mishum desmichi? Or is it because of
its thickness? That even if it doesn't have this idea to pull
back and be connected, but being very thick is enough to define
as a food. והכי הסמיכין, Vehachi hasmichin, and here it's thick. Now
just to tell you what where the גמרא's Gemara gonna go, it
says for בית שמאי Beit Shammai it's clear that the idea is
this רירי, riri, because בית שמאי Beit Shammai talk about the fact
that if you were to stop stop it, some of it would
pull back. Okay. But the question is according to בית הלל, Beit
Hillel, according to the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma that mentions just for
honey. Do they also agree that it needs to be able to
be pulled back, and בית שמאי Beit Shammai just says, you know,
you know, even stuffing that's not as sticky as honey could also,
but they're all agreeing that the criteria is this idea of רירי,
riri, that some of it sticks back? Or is the תנא קמא
Tanna Kamma saying it's not about sticking back at all? It's about
thickness, okay, very, very thick. So maybe your בית שמאי, Beit Shammai,
your oatmeal isn't thick enough and we don't care about the sticky
factor, what we care about is the thickness factor. So that's the
גמרא's Gemara question. According to the תנא קמא, Tanna Kamma, בית שמאי
Beit Shammai it's clear that the sticky factor's important. But according to
the תנא קמא, Tanna Kamma, maybe just the thickness is what's key.
So let's take a look. So what's the story? אמר רבא, Amar
Rava, תא שמע, ta shema, come and hear. חלב המת Chelev hamet
שהוא שלם. shehu shalem. You have the actual fat of a dead
body which is full, which is whole, it's the minimum, minimum amount
that's necessary for טומאה. Okay. והתיכו, Vehiticho, and then it was liquefied.
טמא, Tamei, it remains טמא. tamei. Okay, even in its liquefied form.
היה מפורד והתיכו, Haya meforad vehiticho, if it were separate, if you
didn't have a minimum amount, and it was separated into pieces and
then you liquefied it and put it all together, טהור. tahor. It's
טהור. tahor. Now the reason for that, the second part is not
relevant for us. The reason for that is its general question, which
is if something loses its טומאה because it has less than a
minimum size, can it regain that טומאה once you have the minimum
size? You took a כזית kezayit of a מת, and you separated
it into two halves, right? As a physical object, neither one has
enough. Okay? So if I were to touch it, I'd be טהור.
tahor What if I went ahead and put them back together and
I touch it? Am I טמא tamei or not? So that's a
question. Okay? This is assuming that you would not be טמא tamei
in that case. But now, תוספות points out, and this is very
complicated, that there are other cases where it actually seems that you
are טמא. tamei. So תוספות actually says it depends how the טומאה's
being conducted. If those two חצי כזיתים chatzi kezayitim of a מת
are under a same tent, you don't have to consider them to
be one object, or let's put it this way: the act of
the tent being on top of them is sort of like seen
as like one act, and therefore in that case you would be
טמא. tamei. But if they were two halves, when they were two
halves, for me to be טמא tamei through touching. Even if I
put them together and I touch them both at once, it would
sort of be like two acts combined in one, okay? Because once
they're physically different pieces, it's seen as separate acts of touching. So
therefore, maybe then, even after I combine them and I touch them,
I will still be טהור tahor through touch. All right, so that's
just to give you a little footnote on this. It's very complicated,
this idea of when they get separated and recombined, will you become
טמא tamei again? This משנה Mishnah's assuming that at least for touch
purposes or whatever you will not. That's the idea if it was
separated and recombined. We're not interested in the separated and recombined. We're
interested in when it was whole and liquefied, it remains טמא. tamei.
Okay, now, how is that relevant for us? Let's take a look.
It says, ואי סלקא דעתך v'isalka da'atach אין ניצוק לאוכלין, ein nitzok
l'ochlin, if you would think that things that were food—again, this חלב
cheilev is being considered like food, it started off as a solid—and
you would say that it's not considered combined, you know, and one
unit when it becomes liquefied, so שלם בביתוני נמי יטהר. shalam b'vitchoni
nami yitaher. You should be טהור tahor. if it's liquefied, because even
once it's liquefied—now here's a surprising thing, right? Which is, it's one
thing if I am pouring something to say that the stuff at
the top is טהור. Let's say I'm not pouring something. Let's say
I've got my cup of coffee here and some מצורע metzora touches
it, or right, some type of a נבילה neveila touches it. What's
the story about the coffee at the bottom? Right? So what would
you say there? Would there be something in us that I think
more naturally would be inclined to say, well, that's one unit. Oh,
damn it! Sorry! We'll have to edit that out. Okay, can somebody
get me a towel? Is there a paper towel? Oh God. I
knew I should not use a full cup of coffee for that
demonstration. Oh, darn. Do you need more towels? Yes, yes, I'm okay.
All right, it shows that the גמרא Gemara's been used. All right,
anyway, so now we see that was a purposeful demonstration to show
that coffee is not one unit! Because only some of the coffee—notice
how only some of the coffee came out there. Anyway, so that
was stupid of me. Thank you. That was really stupid of me.
Anyway, so, thank you. Anyway, so, okay. So the point being that
this is assuming, now that we've demonstrated it, this is assuming that
even in a cup, even in one container, if we say that
liquid is not combined, then that would be true about the liquid
at the bottom of the container. You touch the liquid at the
top of the container, the liquid at the bottom of the container
is not טמא. tamei. Okay? Because liquid is not combined, regardless of
if you're pouring it or it doesn't matter if it's all in
a cup. So now the question is, the person took this fat
and dissolved it, and then they touch the fat, right? And they
say it's a source of טומאה, but if it's not combined, they're
not touching the full amount. Some of the fat is at the
bottom of the container and some of the fat is at the
top of the container. Right? The liquefied fat, the liquefied fat. Are
you dealing only with liquid? Like, shouldn't the bottom of—this is all
liquid, shouldn't the bottom be included if it's all—well, that's what I
was—that's exactly what I was saying, that what this גמרא Gemara's showing
you is that the issue about liquid not being one unit is
not only when you're pouring the liquid. Even if it's stable and
in a cup, it's not considered one unit. That's the assumption here.
And therefore it says that if you basically have liquefied this, right?
So then why does it remain a source of טומאה? It's not
all combined as one unit. Right? It's become liquid now and it's
not—is that counterintuitive? It is counterintuitive. I mean, normally we talk about
ניצוק nitzok actually being poured. Okay? It is true because, you know,
I mean, you know, so, so that is true that normally you
think it's the fact that it's being poured that makes you sort
of see them as separate. Now, it could be תוספות tries to
discuss that maybe what's going on here is some assumption that somehow
a little piece separated in the cooking, like I don't know, splattered
out and then recombined, so maybe that's part of the idea. It's
not exactly clear. Let's read the conclusion. But they're arguing right now,
at this moment it's אין ניצוק לאוכלין, ein nitzok l'ochlin, right? And
you're—and so why is this all one unit? It's not because you're
pouring it, it could be stable in the cup. That's what it
seems to be, which is very right. So in other words, it's
just a bunch of infinite number of little drops, it's not one.
That is what it seems. So let's read it. I mean, so
the גמרא Gemara says like this. So it says, אמר רבי זירא,
Amar Rabbi Zeira, so let's just finish, get to the answer. אנא
ומר בריה דרבינא תרגימנא, Anu u'mar brai d'Ravina targumina, I and the
son of Ravina explained it. הכא במאי עסקינן, Hacha b'mai askinan, what
are we talking about here? כגון דבהדי דמרתח ליה, Kegon d'bahadi d'martach
lei, as you're liquefying it, סליק עמודא דנורא לפומא דמנא, salik amuda
d'nura l'puma d'mana, the fire, the flame of fire sort of reached
the opening of the vessel that you were cooking it in, וקרש,
v'karash, and it congealed it, דאיתא כולה גבי הדדי, d'itah kulla gabi
hadadi, that it's all sort of congealed and together, and therefore we're
not talking that it's really fully liquefied, which is of course not
the פשט. p'shat. The פשט p'shat says you liquefied it. And he's
saying, yeah, but in the process of liquefying it, it also re-congealed.
solidified. So that's his answer. If you remove the fire? No, בהדי
דסליק, bahadi de-salik, no, the, while you're, while you're cooking it סליק,
salik, the flame of fire leapt up, rose up and burned the,
you know, and you know, got to the opening of the vessel
and caused it all really to solidify. That doesn't make sense. What
can I tell you? Solidify, that's why I read סליק. salik. No,
the heat of the fire can cause the liquid to... No, I
guess if it burns it and it chars it or something. I
mean like the more you, sometimes like things get thicker the more
you heat it up. Something like that. Like pudding and stuff that
happens on the top of it. Right. Alright, let's just read the
last answer. אמר ליה רבינא לרב אשי, amar lei Ravina le-Rav Ashi,
so Ravina said to Rav Ashi, תא שמע, ta shema, so we're
going to still try to answer this question. בית שמאי אומרים אף
המקוה של גריסין ושל פול ממה שהן סולין לאחוריהן. Beit Shammai omrim
af hamikveh shel grisin veshel pul mimeshehen sollin leachoreihen. So you see
for בית שמאי, Beit Shammai, the reason it's combined is because it
pulls back and it's sticky, okay? So you see that it's about
being, not about being thick, but about being sticky. So the גמרא
Gemara says מידי איריא, midi irya, is that relevant? התם משום דסמיכין
הכא משום רירי. hasam mishum desmichin hacha mishum riri. Yes, there, meaning
we're talking, meaning בית שמאי Beit Shammai's issue is about the רירי,
riri, is about the stickiness factor, but we're asking about maybe the
תנא קמא Tanna Kamma is not about that. I mean it's funny
to read this into words, but essentially the answer is, sure, for
בית שמאי Beit Shammai it's about the stickiness, but who knows what
the honey is for the תנא קמא; Tanna Kamma; is it about
stickiness or is it about thickness? So therefore in the end of
the day, we don't know for the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma what
is the story of something is very, very thick but not sticky.
It certainly sounds like it's about its stickiness because honey is also
sticky, so it's hard to imagine that it's just about thickness, but
the גמרא Gemara leaves that as an unanswered question. Okay.